{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One leader of this kingdom was called the “mute king,” and a curse believed to be cast on the ruling dynasty of this kingdom supposedly explains why alternating generations of its Wadiyar Dynasty never hadchildren.Thefirstiron-casedrocketswereusedbythiskingdom,leadingtheBritishtoreverse-engineer the Congreve Rocket. This kingdom’s ruler Hyder Ali fought the Maratha Confederacy and the British East India Company. Tipu Sultan ruled, for ten points, what kingdom in southern India?",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Mysore"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leo VI the Wise claimed to have invented a hand siphon for use with this material, and dromon galleys had mounted siphons on their prow to launch this weapon. Scientists have doubted phosphine’s potential to be used in this weapon, as its reaction with water isn’t violent enough. Naphtha, quicklime, and sulfur are among the various candidates for the possible ingredients of, for ten points, what seemingly magic incendiary weapon that was used by the Byzantines until knowledge of its production was lost around the 12th century?",
      "answer": "Greek fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man declared that “the road to holiness necessarily passes through the world of action” in his memoirs, titled Markings. The Soviet Union attempted to unseat this man with a three-person “troika” with veto power. Union Miniere may have killed this man, whose DC-6 was shot down as he flew for peace talks with Moise Tshombe’s Katangese troops. He was posthumously awarded the Nobel Peace Prize for his work in the Congo Crisis. For ten points, identify this Swedish politician, the second UN Secretary-General.",
      "answer": "Dag Hammarskjold"
    },
    {
      "question": "Crime boss Charles Binaggio operated in this state, hoping to take over local politics to allow the mob to grow. Racially restrictive housing contracts were found to be illegal in a case that arose from this state, Shelley v. Kramer. Thomas Pendergast ran a political machine in this state, leading Harry Truman to be known as “the Senator from Pendergast.” For ten points, name this state that entered the Union with Maine as part of a namesake 1820 compromise.",
      "answer": "Missouri"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ship Primrose was attacked in this island chain, which was once colonized by Austria as Theresia. Sher Ali Afridi stabbed the 6th Lord Mayo to death in these islands, where a prison known as the “black waters” was used to house British political prisoners. The Cellular Jail was in this island chain, where missionary John Allen Chau was killed by the Sentinelese in 2018. Port Blair is the capital of, for ten points, what island chain west of Myanmar whose indigenous people are some of the last uncontacted people in the world?",
      "answer": [
        "Andaman Islands",
        "Andaman and Nicobar islands"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Archaeologist John Marshall claims that the Pashupati seal depicts a “proto” version of this god surrounded by animals. This god’s name originally was applied as an epithet to the Vedic god Rudra, with whom this god was syncretized. This god is depicted with a third eye, which he used to destroy the love god Kama. Parvati is the wife of, for ten points, what Hindu destroyer god who makes up the Trimurti with Vishnu and Brahma?",
      "answer": "Shiva or Siva"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gained the support of Century magazine editor Robert Johnson after the two of them took a trip to Tuolumne [too-AWL-um-nee] Meadows. This man worked with Henry Senger to form a resistance group to the Hetch Hetchy Dam. A famous photograph of this man shows him standing atop Glacier Point with Theodore Roosevelt. In 1906, this man successfully campaigned for Yosemite to be put under federal control. For ten points, name this Scottish-American naturalist who founded the Sierra Club.",
      "answer": "John Muir"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler debated Otanes and Megazubus over different governmental systems until he was chosen to be king because his slave Oebares made his horse neigh first at sunrise. This ruler overthrew Bardiya, who was possibly impersonated by Gaumata. Nebuchadnezzar III fought a ruler of this name, who created the first satrapies from a tax system inherited by Cyrus the Great. The Behistun Inscription was created by, for ten points, what ruler who led the first Persian invasion of Greece?",
      "answer": [
        "Darius the Great",
        "Darius I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As a result of a dispute with Peter Ludvig Moller, this thinker was harassed on the streets of his hometown in what became known as the Corsair Affair. In one book, this thinker claimed that only by “virtue of the absurd” were movements of faith possible. This thinker used the teleological suspension of the ethical to justify Abraham’s sacrifice of Isaac. For ten points, name this Danish thinker who discussed the “leap of faith” and wrote Fear and Trembling.",
      "answer": "Soren Kierkegaard"
    },
    {
      "question": "The perpetrators of this event avoided jail after a report sent by Aaron Briggs was not believed by Governor Joseph Wanton. Prior to this event, William Dudingston sparked anger by rerouting a rum shipment from the Fortune. The target of this event had run aground while chasing the Hannah near Warwick, allowing John Brown and Abraham Whipple to burn it down. For ten points, name this early act of colonial violence, a 1772 attack on a British vessel in Rhode Island.",
      "answer": "Gaspee Affair"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Wulfing Cache artifacts may have originated at a site in this city that housed several workshops specializing in copper pieces. A circular wooden “henge” once sat on what is now a burial site south of this city; that site contained the grave of a man who was buried atop beads arranged to resemble a falcon. Birdman artifacts typical of this city’s Mississippian culture have been found in excavations of this city’s Mound 72. For ten points, name this pre-Columbian city in modern Illinois, east of St Louis.",
        "answer": [
          "Cahokia",
          "Cahokia Mounds"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The largest mound in Cahokia is this double-terraced mound on the edge of the central palisade which has been named for the Trappists who settled on it in the early 1800s.",
        "answer": "Monks Mound"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of this campaign’s initiatives, the city of Akmolinsk was renamed Tselinograd. This campaign mandated the construction of new sovkhozes in the Caucasus and Siberia. Dry conditions in Kazakhstan prevented the successful development of monoculture during this campaign, which sought to catch the UnitedStatesingrainproductionby1960.Fortenpoints,namethiscampaigninwhichNikitaKhrushchev attempted to bolster the agricultural output of the Soviet Union by plowing previously unused farmland.",
        "answer": [
          "Virgin Lands Campaign",
          "Osvoyeniye tseliny"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Some critics believed Khrushchev developed the Virgin Lands Campaign as a way to steal credit from this politician, who served as premier without party leadership for two years until he was removed in a power struggle in 1955. This man’s 1957 coup against Khrushchev failed.",
        "answer": "Georgy Malenkov"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Gone With the Wind was re-released in 1961 in part to re-take the US box office record from this film. Around the World in 80 Days and The King and I beat this film in all of its nominated Oscar categories except Best Special Effects, which it won in part for a scene created by playing footage of spilling water backwards. ABC has annually broadcast this film on Easter weekend since 1973. Cecil B. DeMille’s last film was, for ten points, what epic about the life of Moses?",
        "answer": "The Ten Commandments"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ten Commandments stars this man as Moses. He also starred in Ben-Hur, and he led the National Rifle Association for five years before his death in 2008.",
        "answer": [
          "Charlton Heston",
          "John Charles Carter"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Russian memorial at this battle also commemorates Santarosa. Frank Abney Hastings led a night raid during this battle, in which the Scipion came under heavy attack. Bonfires were lit on Mount Parnassos after this battle, which was described by George IV as an “untoward event.” Henri de Rigny and Edward Codrington led the winning forces at this battle, which took place at Sphacteria inlet near Pylos. For ten points, name this 1827 battle, an Ottoman loss during the Greek War of Independence, that was the last battle between wooden ships.",
        "answer": "Battle of Navarino"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This son of Muhammad Ali ordered Codrington’s allied fleet to leave Navarino Bay; Codrington warned that they had come peacefully but would destroy this man’s fleet if they attacked. That happened.",
        "answer": "Ibrahim Pasha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A senator from this state abandoned his isolationism and called the Japanese “ignoble, barbarous, and cruel” after viewing the “Bloody Saturday” photograph; that man from this state introduced the Rural Electrification Act in Congress and, with a future New York mayor, co-named a bill against yellow dog contracts. This state was represented in the House by a man who resigned from Woodrow Wilson’s cabinet after the Lusitania sinking and gave the “Cross of Gold” speech. For ten points, name this home state of William Jennings Bryan, the “Boy Orator of the Platte,” who represented the capital city of Lincoln.",
        "answer": "Nebraska"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Nebraska senator co-sponsored a 1932 labor law with Fiorello LaGuardia and supported much of the New Deal, particularly the TVA.",
        "answer": "George W. Norris"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mohamed Hamdan Dagalo has led one of the groups in this conflict, a militia of Abbala and Baggara people known as “evil men on horseback.” The Justice and Equality Movement and the SLA are rebel groups opposed by government forces in this conflict. UN peacekeepers have been based in el-Fashir and Nyala during this conflict, in which hundreds of thousands of people have been killed. Omar al-Bashir carried out, for ten points, what crime against humanity in western Sudan?",
        "answer": "Darfur genocide or Darfur War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This militia, whose name loosely translates to “evil men on horseback,” has committed numerous war crimes during the Darfur genocide.",
        "answer": "Janjaweed"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Robinson, a speaker for this group, faced an estate scandal after prot´eg´e Edmund Pendleton discovered debts. This group created eight shires, and its first meeting was cut short by a malaria outbreak. This assembly, which met at the Wren Building, passed the 1705 Slave Codes, stripping rights from African Americans, to prevent a repeat of Bacon’s Rebellion. The “Give me liberty or give me death” speech was given by Patrick Henry at a meeting of, for ten points, what legislative body of colonial Virginia?",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peyton, a member of this family, served as the last Speaker of the House of Burgesses. Another member of this family served in two positions in George Washington’s Cabinet.",
        "answer": [
          "Randolph",
          "Peyton and/or Edmund Randolph"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this movement, the Bishop of Worms tried to shelter Jews in his house and Ruthard of Mainz fought alongside his personal guard to defend Jews during the Rhineland massacres, which were perpetrated by men under Count Emicho, a leader of this movement. Another leader of this movement, WalterSansAvoir,causedtensionsbylootingoutsideofBelgrade.Thepeasantforcewithinthismovement was defeated at Civetot by Kilij Arslan. Peter the Hermit led peasants in a poorly-organized movement during, for ten points, what 1095-1099 campaign to recapture the Holy Land?",
        "answer": [
          "First Crusade",
          "People’s Crusade and/or Peasant’s Crusade and/or Pauper’s Crusade until “peasant” is read, and"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The People’s Crusade and First Crusade were each inspired by this meeting, where Pope Urban II cried “Deus Vult!”",
        "answer": "Council of Clermont"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Political Cartoons",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Company, founded by John Rockefeller, that was depicted as a giant octopus destroying Washington, DC.",
          "answer": "Standard Oil Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founding Father who created the “Join, or Die” cartoon of a segmented snake.",
          "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
        },
        {
          "question": "1807 Act represented as “this cursed Ograbme” biting a merchant.",
          "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boss of Tammany Hall who was depicted with a money bag for a head in one cartoon.",
          "answer": "William Magear “Boss” Tweed"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who created that cartoon, many others attacking Tammany Hall, and the elephant symbol for the GOP.",
          "answer": "Thomas Nast"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York-based political magazine that employed that cartoonist and thoroughly covered the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Harper’s Weekly, A Journal of Civilization"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three word name of a William Charles cartoon attacking the Hartford Convention.",
          "answer": "LEAP NO LEAP"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cartoonist for the Washington Post who coined the term McCarthyism.",
          "answer": [
            "Herbert Lawrence Block",
            "Herblock"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assassination of Franz Ferdinand",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War that was sparked by his assassination in 1914.",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in modern Bosnia where he was shot and killed.",
          "answer": "Sarajevo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attacker who fatally shot Franz Ferdinand and his wife, Sophie.",
          "answer": "Gavrilo Princip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian emperor and uncle of Franz Ferdinand who had planned war with Serbia before the assassination.",
          "answer": [
            "Franz Josef I",
            "Francis Joseph I",
            "do not"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian nationalist group led by Apis whose young Bosnian members plotted the assassination.",
          "answer": [
            "Black Hand",
            "Unification",
            "Death"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomatic note issued by Austria-Hungary a month after the attack; Serbia’s refusal to fully comply led to war.",
          "answer": "July Ultimatum"
        },
        {
          "question": "1917 trial in Greece where the leaders of that group were court martialed.",
          "answer": "Salonika Trial"
        },
        {
          "question": "Assassin whose hand grenade missed Franz Ferdinand and whose ensuing suicide attempts didn’t work.",
          "answer": "Nedeljko Cabrinovi´c , but be lenient"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Afghanistan",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city, captured by the Northern Alliance in 2001.",
          "answer": "Kabul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruling power in Afghanistan that was ousted in the 2001 US invasion.",
          "answer": [
            "Taliban",
            "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious figure that was the subject of two massive statues that were dynamited in Bamiyan by that group.",
          "answer": [
            "Buddha",
            "Siddhartha Gautama",
            "Bamiyan Buddhas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for US-backed Afghan guerrilla fighters during the Soviet invasion.",
          "answer": "mujahideen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Global organization, developed at the 1955 Bandung Conference, that it joined in 1961.",
          "answer": "Non-Aligned Movement"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was succeeded by Ashraf Ghani in 2014 after nearly 13 years in power.",
          "answer": "Hamid Karzai"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 1978 coup in which President Mohammed Daoud Khan and his family were murdered.",
          "answer": "Saur Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final King of Afghanistan, who was deposed in 1973.",
          "answer": "Mohammed Zahir Shah"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An author from this country was imprisoned for writing the article “Thoughts on March 8,” which criticized this country’s leaders for leaving their wives. Another author from this country wrote the novels To Live and (20 pts)",
        "Brothers, which depict struggle sessions in this country. Another author from this country wrote the novel (10 pts)",
        "Red Sorghum, which ends with a war between this country and Japan. For ten points, name this home country of Ding Ling, Yu Hua, and Mo Yan, who depicted this country’s revolution under Mao Zedong."
      ],
      "answer": "People’s Republic of China or Zhongguo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this event, one victim issued a statement claiming that the American people had to decide “Whether ours shall continue to be a government of laws and not of men.” Leon Jaworski took over the central figure’s position after this event, which occurred after a refusal of the (20 pts)",
        "Stennis Compromise. Expansion of an investigation into the activities of the Plumbers was one of the causes of this event, which was ultimately carried out by (10 pts)",
        "acting Attorney General Robert Bork. For ten points, name this event in which Archibald Cox was fired while acting as special prosecutor of the Watergate investigation."
      ],
      "answer": "Saturday Night Massacre"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man supposedly fell into a “violent passion” and massacred the people of Limoges [lim-ohzh]. This man was denied reinforcements against the Duke of Alencon after the king declared “let the (20 pts)",
        "boy win his spurs.” John II demanded this man’s surrender after outflanking him, but this man declined and instead routed John’s forces at (10 pts)",
        "Poitiers [pwa-tee-ay]. This heir to Edward III died of dysentery in 1376, allowing Richard II to take the throne instead. For ten points, name this English general of the Hundred Years’ War who became known for his dark armor."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edward the Black Prince",
        "Edward of Woodstock"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist created an oil painting in which a bicyclist frightens horses drawing a carriage as they maneuver out of the way. This artist of The Right of the Road depicted the opening of the Wounded Knee massacre in an illustration for (20 pts)",
        "Harper’s Weekly. This artist, who sometimes collaborated with his friend, author Owen Wister, created a bronze sculpture depicting a man (10 pts)",
        "struggling to keep hold of the mane of a horse. For ten points, name this artist known for his scenes of the Old American West, such as The Bronco Buster."
      ],
      "answer": "Frederic Remington"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prior to this event, its perpetrator admitted that he was “going to strike a strong blow. Things are going to get hot,” and, in a meeting with Jean Drepeau, noted, “I have to speak to those people who are calling for me.” In the wake of this event, (20 pts)",
        "Pierre Trudeau was labeled “the enemy of the ‘French fact’”. This incident, which took place during Expo 67, took place on a balcony at (10 pts)",
        "Montreal City Hall. Lester Pearson issued the retort “The people of Canada are free” after, for ten points, what July 1967 international incident in which Charles de Gaulle stoked Qu´eb´ecois nationalism with a controversial four-word phrase?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle proclaiming Vive le Qu´ebec libre! or Long live free Qu´ebec!",
        "prompt on descriptions of de Gaulle visiting Montreal, Canada"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer included characters like Human Frailty in his Homer-inspired opera The Return of Ulysses to his Homeland. This composer used an excerpt from Jerusalem Delivered for an opera that contains one of the (20 pts)",
        "earliest uses of tremolo. Ottavia sings “Addio, Roma” in an opera by this composer about the crowning of Nero’s mistress, The Coronation of Poppea. (10 pts)",
        "Eurydice fails to return to the mortal world in the most famous work by, for ten points, what Italian composer of L’Orfeo, one of the earliest surviving operas?"
      ],
      "answer": "Claudio Giovanni Antonio Monteverdi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Speculation about this event theorizes that the man who ordered it wished to make amends after his affair with Lida Baarova. A postcard bearing the words “I must protest so that the whole world hears my protest” was found in the pocket of (20 pts)",
        "Herschel Grynszpan, whose assassination of Ernst vom Rath, a diplomat in Paris, provided the pretext for this event. The (10 pts)",
        "SA carried out, for ten points, what 1938 event in which the Nazi government promoted a pogrom against synagogues and Jewish homes?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kristallnacht",
        "Night of Broken Glass"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, Charles Wellford revealed a road to cartographer Jedidiah Hotchkiss to shieldforcesfromenemypickets.JohnReynoldsmadeadaylightmarchtotheRappahannock in this battle while Jubal Early desperately tried to keep John (20 pts)",
        "Sedgwick at bay. Prior to this battle, a general commented, “My plans are perfect. May God have (10 pts)",
        "mercy on General Lee, for I will have none.” Joseph Hooker lost despite a Union numerical advantage at, for ten points, what May 1863 battle near Fredericksburg where friendly fire caused the death of “Stonewall” Jackson?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Chancellorsville"
    }
  ]
}